A Finding Aid to the Robert W. White Papers, 1889-2003, bulk 1915-2003, in the Archives of American Art AAA.whiterobe
Archives of American Art
Robert W. White papers
bulk 1915-2003
1889-2003
AAA.whiterobe
Archives of American Art
8.4 Linear feet
The papers of New York sculptor Robert White measure 8.4 linear feet and date from 1889-2003, with the bulk of the material from 1915-2003. The collection documents White's varied career as a sculptor, educator, painter, and illustrator through biographical material; extensive correspondence; project files; personal business records; notes and writings; sketchbooks and sketches by Robert White and others; printed material; audiovisual material; artifacts; and photographs.
White, Robert
Provenance
The Robert W. White Papers were donated in 2003 by Claire Nicolas White, widow of Robert White.
Restrictions on Access
Use of the original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Robert Winthrop White (1921-2002) lived and worked in St. James, New York and was primarily known as a sculptor and educator.
He was the son of the architect, Lawrence Grant White (1887-1956) and Bessie Chanler White. Stanford White (1853-1906), Robert's grandfather, was one of the founding partners in the prominent New York City architectural firm, McKim, White, and Mead.
As a youth, Robert White traveled to Munich, Germany to study woodcarving, sculpture, and painting. In 1935, he entered Portsmouth Priory School in Rhode Island. From 1938-1942, he was enrolled in the Rhode Island School of Design, where his mentors were Walter Raemisch in sculpture and John Howard Benson in calligraphy. In World War II, White served as chief boatswain's mate in the United States Coast Guard and later worked in the Office of Strategic Services (OSS). At the end of the war, White continued his training in sculpture and painting. In 1947, Robert White married Clare Nicolas, daughter of the painter and stained glass master, Joep Nicolas and the sculptor, Suzanne Nicolas.
Robert White, influenced by the classical techniques of the Renaissance artists, worked in various media, such as bronze, stone, plaster, terra-cotta, and wood. His subjects included portrait, figure, and life studies; animals; and dancers. Robert White also was an illustrator. He illustrated works by Laura Spencer Pope, William Styron, and others. White also illustrated two collections of his own poems, Casques and Dust and Palace: The Story of A Friendship that were privately published before his death in 2002.
Robert White held teaching positions at several universities and schools, including the Suffolk Museum of Art, the Parsons School of Design, and the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture. From 1967-1987, White was an associate professor at the State University of New York at Stony Brook.
White exhibited his work in museums and galleries in the United States and abroad, including Artists Choice Museum, Artist's Gallery, Benson Gallery, Boston Athenaeum, Gallery North, Hartwick College Museum, Nassau County Museum of Fine Art, Patricia Fleischmann Gallery, Rijksakademie Van Beeldende, State University of New York at Stony Brook, and the Suffolk Museum and Carriage House, among others. Robert White was represented by the Davis Gallery, Graham Gallery, and Graham Modern in New York City.
Robert White's private and public commissions included works for the American Battle Monuments Commission, Amyas Ames, Theodore Cremer, John Marquand, Peabody Museum, State University of New York, William Styron, and Xerox Corporation. His work can be viewed in the collections of the Boston Athenaeum, Brooklyn Museum, Civici Musei 3 Gallerie di Storia e Arte, Heckscher Museum, and the Rhode Island School of Design. Robert White was the recipient of the Laurel Gallery's "New Talent" exhibition prize, 1948; American Academy's Rome Prize, 1952-1954; and the Proctor Memorial Prize at the National Academy of Design, 1962, 1982. He was also awarded grants from the Tiffany Foundation, 1950 and the Fairfield Foundation, 1968. From 1952-1955, White was a fellow of the American Academy in Rome, where he also served as an artist-in-residence from 1969-1970. Robert White was a member of the American Academy in Rome, the Augustus Saint Gaudens Memorial, Century Association, and the National Academy of Design.
Robert White continued to work on the family estate in St. James, New York until his death in 2002.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York sculptor Robert White measure 8.4 linear feet and date from 1889-2003, with the bulk of the material from 1915-2003. The collection documents White's varied career as a sculptor, educator, painter, and illustrator through biographical material; extensive correspondence; project files; personal business records; notes and writings; sketchbooks and sketches by Robert White and others; printed material; audiovisual material; artifacts; and photographs.
Scattered biographical materials include a curriculum vitae, documentation relating to White's service in the U.S. Coast Guard, a certificate of appreciation, and a memorial card for White's daughter, Natalie Laura White.
Correspondence contains primarily incoming letters from family and friends, and from clients, galleries, museums, arts organizations, students, and university administrators. Spanning over a seventy year period, family and friends correspondence centers on daily activities, events, and work. There is extensive correspondence from Robert White's parents, Lawrence Grant White and Bessie Chanler White and from Claire Nicolas White and her family. Other correspondents include Gil Franklin, Walker Hancock, Jim Harrison, Susan Hobbes, Willard R. Huntington, Ben LaFarge, Ward Lamb, Suzannah Lessard, Peter Matthiessen, Walker O'Cain, Mark and Katja Oxman, Frank C. Platt, Laura Spencer Pope, Paul and Ellen Resika, Paul Russotto, Sidney Simon, and William Styron, among others.
General correspondence mostly concerns White's commissions, teaching appointments, and his activities in professional organizations. Also included are letters from family members, friends, and colleagues. Frequent correspondents include: the American Academy in Rome, Amyas Ames, the Augustus Saint Gaudens Memorial, Century Association, Theodore Cremer, Davis Galleries, Patricia Fleischmann, Hugh Fosburgh, Rebekah Harkness Kean, David Garrard Lowe, National Academy of Design, Parsons School of Design, S. Dillon Ripley, the State University of New York at Stony Brook, Steuben Glass, and the Suffolk Museum and Carriage House.
Project files contain materials on Robert White's exhibitions and his commissioned projects. Materials include letters, lists of artwork, notes, price lists, receipts, exhibition schedules, contracts, and loan agreements. Files document White's exhibits at the Davis Galleries, Elaine Benson Gallery, Graham Gallery, Graham Modern, Heckscher Museum, and the State University of New York at Stony Brook. Included are extensive files on White's commissions for the American Battle Monuments Commission, Peabody Museum, and Steuben Glass.
Personal business records include files on Robert White's association with the Augustus Saint Gaudens Memorial and the National Academy of Design; his teaching appointments at the Parsons School of Design, the State University of New York at Stony Brook, and the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture; and his dealings with foundries. There are scattered files on the Whites' St. James, New York property and residence.
Notes and writings contain Robert White's diaries, artist's statements, notebooks, essays on art, lectures, and scattered notes. Also found are writings by Clare White and others.
Sketchbooks and loose sketches contain preliminary studies by Robert White and scattered sketches by others. Printed material houses newspaper clippings and periodicals; exhibition announcements, catalogs, brochures, and posters; press releases and newsletters; and miscellaneous printed material.
Artifacts include two printing blocks: a portrait sculpture of Stephanie White and a landscape image. Audiovisual material consists of an audio CD-disc of a classroom lecture by Robert White at an unidentified venue.
Photographs house images of Robert White; his studio; and snapshots of family and friends, many unidentified. Also included are photographs and slides of artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into ten series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1939-2002 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1923-2002 (Boxes 1-4; 3.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Project Files, 1952-2003 (Boxes 4-5, OV 10; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1889, 1946-2003 (Boxes 5-6, OV 10; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Notes and Writings, 1915, circa 1946-2002 (Boxes 6-7; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 6: Sketchbooks and Sketches, circa 1965-1972 (Boxes 7, 9; 0.3 linear feet
Series 7: Printed Material, 1937-2003 (Boxes 7, 9; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 8: Audiovisual Material, 1973 (Box 7; 1 folder)
Series 9: Artifacts, circa 1965 (Box 7; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 10: Photographs, circa 1940s-2001 (Box 8; 0.5 linear feet)
American Academy in Rome; American Battle Monuments Commission; Ames, Amyas; Century Association (New York, N.Y.); Cremer, Theodore; Davis Galleries; Fleischmann, Patricia; Fosburgh, Hugh, 1916-; Franklin, Gilbert, 1919-; Graham Gallery; Graham Modern (Gallery); Hancock, Walker Kirtland, 1901-; Harrison, Jim; Heckscher Museum; Hobbs, Susan, 1945-; Huntington, Willard R.; Kean, Rebekah Harkness; La Farge, Bancel, 1865-1938; Lamb, Ward; Lessard, Suzannah; Lowe, David, 1933-; Matthiessen, Peter; National Academy of Design (U.S.); O'Cain, Walker; Oxman, Katja; Oxman, Mark; Parsons School of Design--Faculty; Parsons School of Design.; Peabody Museum; Platt, Frank C. (Frank Cheney), 1932-; Pope, Laura Spencer; Resika, Ellen; Resika, Paul; Ripley, Sidney Dillon, 1913-2001; Russotto, Paul; Simon, Sidney, 1917-1997; Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture--School--Faculty; State University of New York at Stony Brook--Faculty; State University of New York at Stony Brook; Steuben Glass, Inc.; Styron, William, 1925-; Suffolk Museum; United States--Coast Guard; White, Bessie Chanler; White, Claire Nicolas, 1925-; White, Lawrence Grant; Artists' studios--Photographs; Diaries; Drawings; Educators--New York (State)--New York; Essays; Illustrators--New York (State)--New York; Lectures; Notebooks; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sculptors--New York (State); Sculpture--Study and teaching; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Sound recordings
- Biographical Material, 1939-2002; Series 1; (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes a certificate of honorable dismissal from the School of St. Gregory in Portsmouth, Rhode Island; documentation relating to White's services for the Offices of Strategic Services; the Veterans' Administration letter for White's eligibility under the G.I. Bill; a memorial card for Natalie Laura White; and copies of Robert White's curriculum vitae.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged in chronological order. Biographical material can be found in Series 5: Notes and Writings and in Series 7: Printed Material.
  - Certificate of Honorable Dismissal, the School of St. Gregory, Portsmouth, Rhode Island, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Transfer Documentation Relating to Robert W. White's Strategic Services Duty, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Veterans' Administration, Robert W. White's Eligibility for G.I. Bill, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Other Biographical Information, 1947-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificate of Appreciation for Service, State University of New York at Stony Brook, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorial Card for Natalie Laura White (1957-1975) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Curriculum Vitae, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1923-2002; Series 2; (Boxes 1-4; 3.8 linear feet)
  This series includes mostly incoming correspondence, drafts of letters, greeting cards, and postcards. Several letters and envelopes are illustrated. Many letters have attachments such as receipts, invoices, exhibition announcements, printed material, and photographs.
  Correspondence is also found in Series 3: Project Files, Series 4: Personal Business Records, and Series 5: Notes and Writings.
  Files are arranged chronologically; undated letters are filed at the end of the subseries. A number of letters are in Dutch, French, German, and Italian.
  The correspondence series is arranged into 2 subseries:
  2.1: Family and Friends Correspondence, 1923-1955
  2.2: General Correspondence, 1950-2002
  - Family and Friends, 1923-1955; 2.1
    This subseries includes letters, postcards, and greeting cards from family, friends, colleagues, and students. Correspondence provides a detailed account of the routine activities and work of family and friends; letters include references to artists, writers, and other prominent individuals, such as Bernard Berenson, Aldous Huxley, Christopher Isherwood, Carl Milles, and Walter Raemish.
    Frequent correspondents include: Gil Franklin, Walker Hancock, Jim Harrison, Susan Hobbes, Bruce Hooten, Willard R. Huntington, Ben LeFarge, Ward Lamb, Suzannah Lessard, John Marquand, Peter Matthiessen, Walker O'Cain, Mark and Katja Oxman, Laura Spencer Pope, Paul and Ellen Resika, Paul Russotto, Sidney Simon, and William Styron. Files also include letters relating to White's activities as an artist and teacher.
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1923-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1930s; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1930s-1940s; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1935-1938; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1939; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1940s (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1940; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1941; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1942; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 27-30)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1945; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1946; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-40)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence (Claire Nicolas White), 1946; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1947; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 49-51)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1952; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 50-52)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1953; (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 53-57)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1954; (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 58-63)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1955; (7 folders) (Box 1, Folder 64-70)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1956; (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1970s; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1972; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1973; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1974; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1975; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1976; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 28-30)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1977; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1978; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1979; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1980s; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1980; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1981; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1982; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1983; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1984; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 49-51)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1985; (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 53-55)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1986; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1987; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence (Valentin Tatransky), 1987-2002; (8 folders) (Box 3, Folder 4-11)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1988; (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 12-15)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1989; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1989-1990; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1990; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1990; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1992; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1993; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1994; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1996; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 35-37)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, circa 1999-2001; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, undated; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 43-44)
    - Family and Friends Correspondence, Loose Envelopes, 1938-1986; (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 45-48)
  - General Correspondence, 1950-2002; 2.2
    This subseries includes correspondence with clients, museums, galleries, and publishers. Interspersed among the files are letters from family, friends, and students. Attachments to letters include loan agreements, purchase orders, receipts, and printed material. Letters to Robert White discuss his work, exhibitions, commissioned projects, and teaching positions.
    Among the correspondents are Amyas Ames, Stan Brodsky, Theodore Cremer, Patricia Fleischman, Willard R. Huntingdon, Rebekah Harkness Kean, David Garrard Lowe, Richard McDermott Miller, Walker O'Cain, Mark Oxman, and Richard Wilbur. Also included are letters from the American Academy in Rome, Brooklyn Museum, Century Association, Contemporary Realist Gallery, Davis Gallery, Grace Borgenicht Gallery, Harkness Ballet, National Academy of Design, State University of New York at Stony Brook, and Steuben Glass. Also found is a draft of Robert White's letter to Jacques Lipchitz.
    - General Correspondence, 1950-1952 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - General Correspondence, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - General Correspondence, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - General Correspondence, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - General Correspondence, 1956; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 53-55)
    - General Correspondence (Steuben Glass), 1957 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - General Correspondence, circa 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1957; (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 2-5)
    - General Correspondence, 1958; (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
    - General Correspondence, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - General Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - General Correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - General Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - General Correspondence, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - General Correspondence, 1969; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
    - General Correspondence, circa 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - General Correspondence, 1970; (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
    - General Correspondence, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - General Correspondence, 1972; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
    - General Correspondence, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - General Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - General Correspondence, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - General Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - General Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - General Correspondence, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - General Correspondence, circa 1980s (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - General Correspondence, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - General Correspondence, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - General Correspondence, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - General Correspondence, 1983; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 35-36)
    - General Correspondence, 1984; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
    - General Correspondence, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - General Correspondence, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - General Correspondence, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - General Correspondence, circa 1988 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - General Correspondence, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - General Correspondence, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - General Correspondence, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - General Correspondence, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - General Correspondence, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - General Correspondence, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - General Correspondence, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - General Correspondence, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - General Correspondence, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - General Correspondence, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - General Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - General Correspondence, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - General Correspondence, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - General Correspondence, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - General Correspondence, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - General Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - General Correspondence, Loose Envelopes, 1950-1979 (Box 4, Folder 59)
- Project Files, 1952-2003; Series 3; (Boxes 4-5, OV 10; 1.2 linear feet)